One plus the welcome survey are
due tomorrow.
Again, as always, I have office
hours after lecture.
So if you'd like some help with
that,
come stop by.
And we also have office hours
both by me and by the IEs and
GSIs during the day tomorrow.
So feel free to stop by.
And then also, we've posted the
solutions to Lab 2.
So make sure to take a close
look at those as well.
The plan for today is to talk
all about this new model that we
briefly talked about on
Tuesday's class, that you played
around with in lab yesterday,
the simple linear regression
model.
That'll be our focus for today.
And then when we come back next
week,
then we will start talking about
ideas from linear algebra, in
particular, what a vector is.
But before we do that,
I want to make sure it's super
clear why we need to introduce
vectors at this point in our
storyline
in the course.
But again, today is going to be
all about the simple linear
regression model.
So at the end of
Tuesday's class I showed you a
picture that looked like this
and I said our goal is to now
build a
Model that can actually use the
time we leave in the mortening
the departure hour That is our X
as an input when making
predictions about our commute
time Which has been our running
example so far this semester Our
goal is to predict how long it's
going to take for us to get to
work That is our commute time
given the time we leave in the
morning
The first model that we studied,
the constant model,
it looked like a flat line.
And then what we discussed at
length over the last two
lectures was where is the
optimal place to put that flat
line?
And the answer that we've
discovered
is that it depends on which loss
function we choose.
If we choose squared loss as our
loss function, then the optimal
place to place that constant
model
was at the average or mean of
the Y values.
If we use absolute loss, Well,
then there's a different
location.
Then it's the median of the y
values.
And what you played around with
in lab yesterday was if you
think of these other loss
functions, well, then there are
other best places to put that
horizontal line.
Now we are dealing with the
simple linear regression model,
which has the form h of xi
equals w0
plus w1 xi.
Someone remind me what these two
things are called, W0 and W1.
What's the name for those?
Kevin?
Parameters.
Parameters, good.
We have two parameters here.
And the question is, well, how
do we pick those parameters so
that the resulting predictions
are as good as they can be?
We should do it in a more
principled way than just
eyeballing it.
And that's where the three-step
modeling recipe comes back into
the picture.
And what was the more formal
term for this three-step
modeling recipe that we
introduced on Tuesday?
Someone remind me.
Started with an E,
sounded kind of fancy.
I don't remember.
What's up?
Empirical risk.
Yeah, good.
Minimization.
That first step involves
choosing a model.
We've now seen two.
Today we are going to pick the
simple linear regression model.
Can you remind me why it's
called simple linear regression?
I commented on this on Tuesday.
Yes, and remind me of your name
again?
Zara.
Yeah,
there's only one input variable.
That's why we're calling it
simple.
Here,
that input variable is denoted
xi.
We know that that means the time
we leave in the morning or the
departure time.
In the future, we will learn
about multiple regression.
The next stage is to choose a
loss function.
Once again, we've seen two of
these, but we're going to pick
the more common choice for now,
which is squared loss,
which returns
is the square difference between
an actual y value
and a predicted y value.
So now,
what would be wrong with me
saying that the third step is
minimizing the loss function?
What's wrong with that in terms
of the terminology we've
introduced here? Why would it be
wrong to say, I'm minimizing my
loss function?
That's my goal.
Why is that wrong?
What's up?
Oh, sorry.
You're up, what's up?
Maaj.
I'm trying to minimize average
loss.
Good, good, good.
That's the key.
Loss measures how close or far
one prediction is to its actual
y value.
We don't care about minimizing
that.
We care about minimizing average
loss across an entire data set.
Remember,
one loss function only tells you
how close or far one prediction
is for one row of your data set.
We care about predictions being
good on average across the whole
data set, which is why we
minimize
average loss
to
find
optimal parameters.
And so one of the last things we
did on Tuesday is we wrote out
what the formula for average
loss looks like when we've
chosen the simple linear
regression model and the squared
loss-loss function.
We had a 1 over n.
Maybe I'll put this in red like
everything else.
I had a 1 over n.
I had a sum symbol,
which went from i equals 1 to n.
Any time we have average loss,
you will see this pattern.
1 over n times the sum,
where i goes from 1 to n.
The things I summed were yi
minus something squared.
And that something,
I replace it with how I'm making
my predictions.
That is the definition of my
model.
And here, that definition is w0
plus w1
xi.
And one of the things we
discussed
is that this is a function on
the right of how many input
variables?
How many input variables are
there for this function on the
right?
Two, w0 and w1.
When before,
when we minimized average loss
and we were finding to find the
best W for the constant model,
the average loss function,
whether that was mean squared
error, or mean absolute error,
or mean 0, 1 loss, which was one
of the examples we talked about
on Tuesday,
all of those were functions of
just one input variable,
W, because we only had one
parameter.
Here we have two parameters.
So this function we are
minimizing
takes two input variables.
So we're here, we're treating
the x's and the y's, that is our
data set, as being some
constant.
As in it is like not a thing
that can change as a result of
anything that we do.
The data set is just provided to
us.
So we're clear on what our goal
is.
Our goal is to find a
combination of w0 and w1 that
make this function,
which we would also call mean
squared error, by the way,
but maybe we'd call it mean
squared error for the simple
linear regression model.
SLR is just simple linear
regression.
Our goal is to find the
combination of inputs that gives
us the lowest possible value
here.
Why is that?
Well, it's because that
combination of w0 and w1
should give us the line that
makes
the best predictions on the data
set that we've collected.
Are we clear on what our goal
is?
OK.
So at the end of Tuesday's
class,
we wrote out this formula for
mean squared error for the
simple linear regression model.
And then I just told you the
parameters that minimized it.
But part of what I want to start
with today is understanding how
one would find those parameters.
And to do that, we need to think
about what does this function
actually look like?
Q, what does this look
like?
So to refresh our memory,
when we were minimizing mean
squared error for the constant
model when we had one parameter,
what did the resulting graph
that we were minimizing look
like?
If one axis was w,
and the other axis was the
output of this function,
what did the graph look like?
Remind me.
A parabola.
A parabola, good.
And what we've studied at length
is the x-axis value
of
the vertex of the parabola.
It tells us what w to plug in to
get to the bottom of the
parabola.
One of the things that I didn't
explicitly say in lecture, but
has maybe become clear by
working on homework one and the
recent labs, is that the
vertical component here, that is
what this is,
also has a familiar name.
What is that?
Like when I plug in the mean of
the y's into this mean squared
error function,
what is the resulting output
called?
It has a name that you've heard
of before.
Yeah?
3 times.
Not quite.
I'm asking for the vertical
position of the vertex,
yes.
But I'm saying,
like,
that position is described in
terms of the data set, using a
familiar term.
Do you know, Andrew?
Chinmay.
I'm looking for something that
is like a formula you can
calculate just given the y's.
Average?
Not quite.
That's the input that minimizes
the function.
I'm asking, what is the
resulting output?
Ankita.
The variance.
Good.
It's the variance of the y.
Why is that?
Well,
look at what happens when I plug
in the average y here.
Well, all this tells me then is
that this is the average squared
distance from the mean,
and that's the definition of the
variance.
And actually, if we take a look
at homework one,
due tomorrow,
this is one of the big ideas.
And actually,
we just answered one of the
questions, which is the last one
here,
part E.
What you do there is you rewrite
mean squared error for the
constant model.
Notice, this is not exactly the
formula that was on the screen
before.
Before, that was sum of yi minus
w squared.
So what we're currently looking
at is a little different.
What I'm saying is that the
formula I wrote before is equal
to this one,
where instead of summing yi
minus w squared,
it's the sum of yi minus y bar,
which is the average or mean of
the y's squared, plus this other
thing that involves the w's.
This is, again,
something that will make more
sense once you work through this
question.
But what we're getting at with
this question
is that this first piece is
the variance of the y's.
So a mean squared error actually
equals the variance of the y's
plus something that depends on
the w.
But you can see, in order to
minimize this overall function,
well, this thing w has no
control over.
It doesn't matter what w is,
this first term can't change.
What w can,
where w does come into play is
the second term.
And if w equals y bar,
well, then that's how you make
this as small as possible, which
means that's how you minimize
that function.
But when w equals y bar,
well, then that matches what we
saw with the calculus-based
approach with y bar, or the
average y,
minimizing this function.
But that means if you plug in w
equals y bar,
this piece goes away,
and then mean squared error is
equal to the variance of the
lies.
So this is an important idea,
one that's talked about in the
notes, and one that I want you
to internalize.
OK?
That was sort of a side quest,
but one that was important for
us to talk about.
Going back to where we are in
today's lecture,
when we were dealing with the
constant model, which had one
parameter,
the graph of mean squared error
looked like a parabola.
And we just talked about some
attributes of that parabola.
Remember now,
we are dealing with the simple
linear regression model.
Well,
it has two parameters,
w0 and w1.
And my question is, what does
this graph on the right,
like what does the graph of this
function look like?
What ideas do we have?
What does the graph of this
function look like?
Alex.
Will it be a paraboloid?
Like,
what makes you say paraboloid?
Like, what are you thinking
about? Paraboloid on both axes
and 3D space.
That's the key that I was
getting at.
We're now looking at a function
in 3D.
Why is that?
Well, it's because there are now
two input variables that can
vary.
For every combination of w0,
imagine this is your w0 axis,
and w1,
there is some mean squared error
for that resulting line that
uses that slope and that
intercept.
I should emphasize this more.
W0 is the intercept of the
resulting
line,
and W1 is the slope.
So all we're trying to do is
find the optimal slope and
intercept.
And this function, it allows me
to plug in any possible choice
of intercept and slope.
We could all think of our own
intercepts and slopes that we
think match the data well.
And this function should tell us
how good or bad our choice was.
And how we would do that is by
telling us the mean squared
error of the line with the slope
and intercept that we chose.
So if you pick a combination,
and you pick a combination, and
you pick a combination, we all
plug our combinations of
intercepts and slopes into this
function.
It should tell us what our mean
squared errors were.
And what the graph ends up
looking like, and I'm going to
show you a 3D view of this in a
second,
is sort of like a bowl shape in
3D.
This is more easily visualized
in the course notes.
So I'm going to go there.
This is at the bottom of chapter
2.1,
but we're going to look at this
in a little bit.
This is what it looks like.
And so like I said before,
for every choice of w0
and w1,
what this shows me is the mean
scored error of the resulting
line's predictions.
So every point on this graph,
if you click it, it tells you,
like,
okay,
you know, where I've currently
clicked,
that corresponds to choosing an
intercept of 151 and a slope of
negative 3.4.
And it's telling me if I chose
that intercept and slope,
the resulting line would have a
mean squared error of 2,602.
Which seems high.
If I choose an intercept of 144
and a slope of negative 11.36,
it's saying, okay, that's
better.
You get a mean squared error of
725.
But it seems like we can do even
better, and better, and better.
And our goal is to find
the intercept and slope at the
very bottom of this graph.
And if you look at this from
underneath,
it's hard to tell that this is
the unique bottom.
It looks like there's a whole
flat line where they're all
equally good.
That's not exactly true.
If you zoom in very closely, you
can do this with your mouse on
the computer.
You'll see that it is truly a
unique minimizer here.
What this is saying is, well, if
you choose a slope of negative
8.18
and an intercept of 142,
well, that's how you get the
mean squared error to be as low
as possible.
And our goal now is to try and
figure out if we can find
formulas that describe the best
intercepting slope for any
general dataset.
But to do that, we're going to
need some more advanced
machinery than we already have,
because so far we've only
discussed how to find minimums
of functions with one input
variable, but now we have
multiple input variables.
Paul,
can you explain again why this
has the added dimension and why
that input variable wasn't
relevant before the second input
variable?
It's because before we were
dealing with the constant model
which only had one parameter.
The only thing you could change
about the constant model was
what height it's drawn at.
Now we're dealing with the model
that has two things,
two aspects that we can change,
the intercept of it and the
slope of it,
which is why this function
should tell us for every
combination of those things we
can change,
the intercept and slope,
what is the model's performance.
Is this for linear specific
linear? Yes.
This is just for the simple
linear regression model.
So if you had a model that had
five parameters,
what dimension would you have to
draw the resulting mean squared
error graph in if it had five
parameters.
Six,
because you need one axis for
every parameter and then another
axis to display the mean squared
error of the resulting
predictions.
And what that means is if we
added even one more parameter
to our simple linear regression
model of making it a multiple
linear regression model, we
couldn't make this graph,
because we would need to be able
to look in 4D, which we can.
By the way, this graph,
now I'll just take a screenshot
and keep it in the iPad notes
here.
This graph is what's called a
loss surface,
which is just the name for the
graph of average loss.
And I'll say,
go play with loss surface
in chapter 2.1.
So what we need to figure out is
how to find the optimal
combination here.
W naught star,
W1 star.
That's going to be our focus for
the next 20 minutes or so.
What questions do we have with
this picture so far before we
get into the weeds of the math?
Are we comfortable with why this
is now in three dimensions?
Whereas the previous thing we
minimized was in two dimensions.
Okay
And again, like one thing I want
to emphasize and maybe I could
have done a better job at adding
another visual to the notes on
this any point on this graph
corresponds to a different
looking line so like this point
might correspond to the line
that looks like this and
This point might correspond to
the line that looks like this
and so on So every one of these
points on here corresponds to a
different line, because the
point corresponds to a
combination of intercept and
slope.
And so by minimizing this graph,
it tells us how to draw the
line.
Is that clear?
OK,
good.
So now the question is, well,
how do we actually do that?
And so as a detour,
we need to discuss an idea
that's going to help us get
there, which is that of a
partial derivative.
I'm curious, how many people
have heard of and used a partial
derivative before?
It's about 60% of people.
That's totally fine if you
haven't, by the way.
It's not something I expected
you to know,
because I don't think it comes
up in calc 1, which is the only
calc class you're required to
have taken before this.
So again,
everything you need to know
about partial derivatives we're
about to talk about.
And this is in chapter 2.2.
By the way, chapter 2, it looks
like it has lots of parts, like
four of them.
But they're all designed to be
four or five of them.
very short.
When I first taught this class,
all five of those subpieces were
in one big notebook.
But it was so big that it
crashed the server that I was
hosting it on, because there was
so many graphs in it.
So I broke it up into lots of
smaller things.
So what I want to do before we
get back to the goal of
minimizing mean squared error
for the simple linear regression
model is I want to start with a
simpler function
with multiple input variables.
Why don't I use more familiar
syntax, Like f of x, y equals
something like x squared plus y
squared over 9.
Just so we see it,
what does this thing look like?
Indeed, this is called a
paraboloid.
Same basic shape as the mean
squared error graph we saw.
It's just that was stretched
weirdly, And this one is like
more symmetric,
okay?
this is the graph we're thinking
about here and
You can see I picked a graph
that again has one unique
minimum
But that's like not guaranteed
It's possible that you could
have a graph in three dimensions
where there isn't one minimum
and we'll see some examples of
that
What if we want to try and find
the coordinates of the X&Y that
get us to the bottom of this
graph?
Well, the thing is, now there
isn't just a single direction
along which the function varies.
Our logic in single variable
calculus was take the
derivative, because that tells
us how quickly the function is
changing at any input,
and set that equal to zero.
Because logic tells us that if
we're looking for the minimum of
the function, it's a point at
which the function isn't
changing there, and that's
because on the left of it it was
decreasing, and on the right of
it, it's increasing.
So we must be at a point where
it's at the bottom,
OK?
I guess that logic also applies
to a maximum, which is why you'd
have to use a second derivative
test.
But here,
there isn't just a single
direction along which the
function varies.
There are two directions.
If you look at it in the x
direction,
it looks like a parabola.
And if you look at it just from
the y direction, it also looks
like a parabola, which is why it
has this overall bowl shape,
OK? So,
instead of there just being one
derivative,
we instead have two partial
derivatives.
Okay, partial derivative is just
the term for derivatives of
functions that have multiple
input variables.
And there is one partial
derivative,
which itself is a function,
for every input variable you
have.
So here we are going to find two
partial derivative functions.
One with respect to x,
and one with respect to y.
So what does a partial
derivative measure?
And I'll show you the
calculation.
We'll work through the math in
just a bit.
What the partial derivative
measures,
actually,
let's work through the math
first, and then make sense of
this graph.
Let me start by writing that.
Suppose f is a function
with multiple input variables.
And let's just say,
for example,
f of x, y, z, so on,
these are just placeholder
names.
The partial derivative
of f
with respect to x,
which has this symbol,
it looks like df over dx, but we
use
this lowercase d symbol in
Greek.
unique, which is what you use
whenever you're dealing with
partial derivatives,
is the the
derivative
where
all other variables
are held
constant.
And so this is like a thing that
you can do mechanically, But
it's like hard to understand
what it actually means and so
we're gonna look at some
examples to make sure you It's
clear what it means to hold
other variables constant okay,
but for now the partial
derivative with respect to X of
this function F is
the derivative of this function
with respect to X if we pretend
Y and Any other variables that
may be here are just constants
like the number seven or
something.
That doesn't mean you can
Erase every Y from the formula.
It just means you treat it like
it doesn't depend on X Okay?
So mechanically, let's look at
what this means in this example.
x squared plus y squared over 9.
And just to make it a little
easier to separate things, why
don't I write it as x squared
over 9 plus y squared over 9.
Let's start by finding the
partial derivative with respect
to x.
And by the way,
this is also a function of both
input variables, or at least it
could be a function of both
input variables.
They may not both involve both,
but they could.
And I will make a little more
sense of what that means in just
a second.
What I need to do now is take
the derivative
of this expression with respect
to x, but I need to pretend y is
a constant.
How would I do that?
Yeah,
what this is going to give me is
2x over 9, okay?
So the y squared over 9, where
did it go?
Well that's like a constant from
the i's of x.
And so this function,
the thing we were taking the
derivative of from x's
perspective just looked like x
squared over 9 plus C,
where C was a constant,
okay?
Now this function is
symmetric in terms of x and y,
in that if you swapped all the
x's and y's it would be the same
function.
So what's the partial with
respect to y?
Yeah,
2y over 9, good.
Excellent.
So what I want to emphasize is
that the partial derivatives are
both functions themselves.
You have to plug in a data
point,
or plug in an input.
Yeah, not a data point, I
shouldn't have said that.
Plug in an input, that is plug
in an x and y,
and then the partial derivative
will tell you something about
that point.
So like, let's pick a point.
For example, let's consider the
point on the graph where x is
equal to minus 3,
and y is equal to 1 by 2.
I picked these because this is
what is used in the visual in
the notes we're about to look
at.
What is the partial with respect
to x at that point?
What does that give me?
Yeah,
negative 6 over 9,
which is negative 2 by 3.
And similarly, what's the
partial with respect to y at
that point,
looks like 1 over 9,
2 times a half over 9.
And just because it'll be useful
in what we're about to look at,
this is roughly minus 0.67.
This is roughly 0.11.
The question is, what does that
actually tell us about the graph
at the point x equals minus 3 y
equals a half.
Well, let's go back to the 3D
view.
First,
focus on this number.
Minus 0.67.
That is the partial derivative
with respect to x at the point
we're looking at.
So now let's go back here.
This will make more sense now.
What I've done is in black here,
what we are looking at is the
point 3,
sorry, negative 3 comma a half
comma Whatever the output is at
that point the specific height
on height value.
We don't really care about it,
right?
Are we clear on what point we're
looking at on the graph here?
Yeah, why?
Do you see a tangent line that
is the orange tangent line here
that is sloped downwards like
what's that trying to convey?
You see this tangent line? It's
sloped downwards.
And you have to look at how I've
rotated the graph.
I've tried to rotate this so
that it looks like a
two-dimensional graph just in
terms of x.
And what are you seeing with
this orange tangent line?
What do you see?
Allison?
It seems like we're taking,
never mind, but it's basically
we're acting like it's in two
dimensions by taking that
partial derivative in a four or
three dimensional graph.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Well, what I'm trying to get at
is that the partial derivative
describes how the function is
changing in one direction if
you,
for a moment, pretend the other
directions aren't changing.
And if you do that,
well, it looks like the orange
tangent line is sloped
downwards.
Do you agree with that?
Now, why is it sloped downwards?
Well, it's because the partial
derivative with respect to x at
that point is negative.
That's why I told you to
remember the number negative
0.67.
So we expected this to go down.
Now, when you're dealing with 3D
graphs, it's important that you
oriented the graph so that the
axes,
or at least if you're looking at
it and trying to interpret it in
this way,
it's important that you orient
the axes so that left Left is
decreasing, right is increasing.
You see the x-axis goes negative
4, negative 2, 0, 2, 4.
I could have rotated it this
way.
Now the x-axis is decreasing and
you'd say, oh, the tangent line
is going up and to the right.
Plus it's because you're looking
at it backwards.
Now what if I look at y
increasing and I try and pretend
x isn't moving?
What do you see about the
tangent line in blue? Is it
sloped up or sloped down?
It's sloped up, but barely.
Like, it's not as steep as the
orange one was sloped downwards.
And why is that?
Kevin?
We found the partial derivative
with respect to y was 0.11.
Yeah, which is roughly six times
lower than, at least in
size,
the partial with respect to x.
So we'd expect it to be less
steep.
And so the idea is that that
partial derivative,
well,
the partial derivatives
together, the one with respect
to x and the one with respect to
y,
tell us, if we pick any point on
here, how quickly the function
is changing in the x direction
and in the y direction, both
independently.
So if you had to guess,
if our goal is to try and find a
minimizer of the function, How
do you think we do that of the
overall function?
How do you think we do that?
Yeah,
you set both partial derivatives
to zero and if you had, you
know, ten input variables you
set all of those partial
derivatives equal to zero.
Okay, so we're gonna get there
in just a little bit.
The sort of confusing thing with
this example, but it's,
I intentionally like to start
with this, is that as we saw
before the partial derivative
with respect to x only involved
x and the partial with respect
to y only involved y.
But it's not always that way.
I just started with a simple
example.
So let's look at a more
complicated example.
Okay.
Here this function g of x y
equals x cubed minus 3 x y
squared plus 2 sine x cos y.
Some random thing I cooked up
just so it would look cool.
If you take its partial
derivative with respect to x and
you take it with respect to y,
we're not going to work through
the algebra of that now,
they both involve both
variables.
So I want that to be clear.
In general, a partial derivative
with respect to one variable
includes all of the variables.
It's just that if you have a
simpler function,
it doesn't have to.
But it could, as we're seeing
here.
Let me put this in the iPad
notes for anyone following along
with that.
Actually, I'm curious,
among everyone here, who has
ever looked at the things I
wrote on my iPad after class?
Okay, enough people look at it
that it's worth making sure
these are good.
Okay.
So the idea here is that
important,
both partial derivatives
can involve both variables.
But then this is a little
confusing to think about when I
said the point of a partial
derivative is that it measures
how the function is changing in
one direction if the others are
constant.
What does that mean if both of
them also involve both
variables?
Well, that's what this next
graph is for.
So there's a lot going on here,
so bear with me.
What this slider does is it lets
us pick a value of y.
And that plain or flat sheet of
paper you're seeing in blue
corresponds to the value of y
we've picked.
You can see when I drag the
slider,
it's moving along the y-axis.
You agree?
So here the slider is at y
equals 1.
So this is saying that gold
curve that you're seeing at the
intersection of the original
graph and the plane y equals 1,
that tells you what the function
looks like if you force y to be
1 and say, OK, I'm going to
remove one variable by forcing y
to be 1.
So now, instead of looking at a
graph in three dimensions, we're
looking at a more familiar graph
in two dimensions.
It's this gold intersection.
Do we all see the gold
intersection?
The partial derivative with
respect to x
just describes the derivative of
that gold function.
But why does the partial
derivative with respect to x
involve y?
Well, it's because for different
y's,
the resulting intersection is
different.
Like, it wouldn't make sense for
this function's derivative, when
y equals 2.2,
to have to be the same as this
function's derivative, when y
equals negative 2.2.
These intersections are all
different.
And so depending on what value
of y you pick to force y to be,
the resulting function's
derivative with respect to x is
different.
So that's why, if you go back up
here, or what we were
visualizing,
is the partial derivative with
respect to x.
And all I was doing with that
slider was just holding y
constant by forcing it to be
whatever value that slider
landed on, and then in
calculating the partial
derivative of that,
or the derivative of that gold
function,
I did it by just plugging in
that constant value of y into
the formula at the bottom of the
screen.
And then,
again,
this gold function is the one
whose derivative the partial
with respect to x measures.
And I only drew this in,
I only drew one of these graphs
with y being a slider just to
illustrate the point,
but to visualize the partial
with respect to y,
well then x would have to be
forced to be constant,
and then different values of x
would lead to different
intersections with that plane
and the function,
and the partial with respect to
y would describe the derivative
of the intersected function.
So this is a complicated idea to
wrap your head around.
I'm not expecting you to just
look at me, talk about this, and
be like, OK, that all makes
sense.
These are all in the notes and
intentionally interactive
because I want you to go into
them after class or right now,
whenever,
and play around with this and
try and make sense of this.
But this is the kind of thing
that is hard to internalize,
and it takes people a long time
to grasp how these things in
three dimensions and higher
dimensions work.
But this is just like the start
of our journey with that.
Do we kind of get what a partial
derivative is and what it means
to force one variable to be
constant? That was the main idea
here.
Here I'm forcing y to be
constant.
And the result is a function
that's in two dimensions rather
than three.
The partial derivative describes
that two dimensional functions
derivative.
Sound OK? All right,
so back to the notes.
I should also add people
following along.
Back to the main idea.
The original function we set out
to try and minimize was this
one.
These functions of x and y were
just sort of simpler examples.
Our goal is to minimize this
function?
Okay first like there's some
context switching involved
because in the previous examples
I showed you of the paraboloid
and or like the x squared plus y
squared over 9 paraboloid and
the one that sine x cos y there
the variables were x and y which
I use because those are just
like the default variables you
think of but here the variables
are not x and y there are w
naught and w1 what's tricky
about this is that there are
also x's and y's in the formula
but now remember you have to
think about the x's and y's as
coming from a data set and being
held constant.
So the graph we are looking at,
it has three axes, but none of
them involve x or y directly.
They're w0, w1, and mean squared
error.
Is that clear?
So we're going back to just so
it is crystal clear.
We're going back to
here.
And so the question is,
how do we find
w0 star and w1 star?
Answer is we take the partial
derivative of this function
with respect to what?
What's the first partial
derivative I'm going to have to
find?
Braden, with respect to w
naught,
and then I'm going to have to
find another one with respect to
w1,
set both equal to zero,
and solve for
w naught and w1.
Both of these partial
derivatives are going to be more
complicated than the ones I
showed to you involving sine x
and goes y,
because they're going to involve
summations.
We're going to have to use the
same logic in that the
derivative of a sum is a sum of
derivatives.
So both of these are going to
involve summations of where i
goes from 1 to n.
When we set both equal to 0,
those both will give us a
condition that the optimal w0
and w1 need to satisfy.
And then using some algebra,
we can find the combination that
satisfies both.
And what we're going to do is
I'll give you the high level
idea of how you find the W0 and
W1.
We will do a little bit of the
work together.
But just so that we don't sit
here doing algebra for another
35 minutes,
I'll give you the high level
idea.
And then you will go look at the
notes to see how it's finished.
And then we'll use the resulting
formulas.
The main thing is I want us to
know where the formulas come
from.
But we will take a break before
we do that.
So while we do that,
let's take attendance.
Everyone knows where the new
attendance form is,
right?
You've got to go to, I'll show
you,
course website,
and click the Attendance button
there.
Right now it says it's not
accepting, but now it says it
is.
Go for it, and I'll give you a
couple minutes here.
And it is 11.14.
We'll start again at 11.19.
So if you want to go to the
bathroom, get water.
Oh
Okay,
let's see if we can get this out
of
the
way.
It'll be set up so that you can
pick a time that doesn't come
from that spot on.
All right.
I'm going to go check in,
I think it's still working on
it.
Okay, right?
Two minutes if you want to
relax.
Thank
you.
It's funny walking around seeing
the hops that people choose to
doom scroll in our
After lecture, it's a prime
time, and I come back and have
like 30 minutes to do that.
It's 11.19,
30 minutes to go.
So like I said, by the way, I
read all the comments you put in
about sort of what has been
going well and what is confusing
about today.
So the first thing I'll say is
that all of this, everything
we've done today has something
to do with this picture
and finding the best line on it.
All the partial derivatives,
calculus stuff has related to
that problem of finding the line
with the best choice of slope
and intercept.
And how we do that is when we
find the line with the best
slope and intercept by figuring
out the intercept and slope
that, if you plugged it into
this function,
give you the smallest possible
value.
And all of the partial
derivative stuff
was helping us understand how we
would find that interceptor
slope.
So again,
make sure to play with the 3D
graphs to get a better
understanding of what a partial
derivative is and what it means
to hold one variable constant.
I guess one important comment
I'll comment on here is that
someone asked, why was it the
case that in this first
function,
the partial derivative with
respect to x only had x.
And the second,
the one with respect to y, only
had y.
But in this more complicated
one, they both had both.
How was I able to separate it?
And the answer is that it's not
because I did anything special.
It's just because that's how the
function was.
The first function,
you could write it as something
is involving just x plus
something involving just y.
It already was separated.
Okay, whereas the second
function is more intertwined.
There's lots of terms that
involve an X and a Y being
multiplied together And there's
no way you can separate that
So it's just a cut like a
consequence of what the function
looks like
Okay, so Like I said, I don't
want to work through all of the
algebra here because it's gonna
burn up all of our remaining
Time I want us to focus on the
high-level ideas know where it
comes from and then you can
review the details
on your own
But like we said the goal
or not the goal, but what we are
going to do is calculate the
partial derivatives.
There are two of them, one with
respect to w0,
one with respect to w1,
set them both equal,
and solve for the resulting
combination of intercept and
slope.
OK.
Let's start with the partial
derivative with
respect to w0.
OK.
So let's work through this here.
What is this going to look like?
What's the first piece in this
partial derivative going to look
like with respect to w0?
My guess is the 1 over n is just
going to stay there.
Yep.
So the mechanics of taking the
derivative are no different.
Like all of the same chain rule,
some product rule, all those
things all still apply.
So like I said, we should expect
for there to still be a 1 over n
times the sum.
Now what's next?
Remember, the way I always think
about this is that the
derivative of box squared with
respect to some other variable
is 2 times whatever is in the
box times the derivative of
whatever is in the box.
We're going to use that
repeatedly once we get it.
OK,
so here, the box is just yi
minus w0 plus w1 xi.
That's what's in the box.
Since that thing is squared,
because it's a squared loss,
I should have the 2 times yi
minus w0 plus w1
xi.
Is that clear?
OK.
What comes afterwards?
Yeah? You have to take the
derivative of the inside part.
Yes.
And what is the derivative of
the inside part with respect to
w0?
p negative 1.
Good.
Because the coefficient on w0,
if you expanded out or you
distributed this minus sign,
would just be negative 1.
Are we clear on where the
negative 1's coming from?
OK, good.
Now,
what about the partial? And I
could simplify this a little
bit,
which I'll do on the next slide.
But what about the partial with
respect to w1?
Most of the logic is still the
same.
I'm still, yeah,
sorry.
Is it like the exact same except
that negative 1 is a negative
xy? Exactly.
That's the only difference.
The 1 over n sum,
2 times the box, all the same.
The only thing that's different
is the derivative of what's in
the box.
And that is not negative 1 now,
it'll be negative xi.
Remember the X's are treated as
constants
Not because yeah, the X's were
always treated as constants in
this situation, okay
Same with the Y's so we have the
1 over n sum
y i minus w naught plus w 1 x i
times negative x i
This is the only difference
Those are both partial
derivatives.
And I'm using shorthand here,
but if I really wanted to be
precise,
I would write w0,
w1 here for both of them.
It's just that usually you don't
do that.
I did it at the start to
emphasize that the partial
derivatives are functions of
both input variables.
Was that your question?
Can you just explain again where
the negative xi came from, why
that replaced the 1?
So up here, I don't know why I'm
doing that because then you can
see that over here.
Over here,
with the first partial
derivative,
it was with respect to w naught.
So I took, again, this
complicated expression,
it's being squared, so the
derivative of it with respect to
w naught is two times the
expression using the power rule,
then And the chain rule says,
then I have to multiply this by
the derivative of that
expression with respect to w
naught,
which is just negative one.
If I'm taking the partial with
respect to w one,
then the first step stays the
same because the derivative of
box squared becomes two box,
but that is times the derivative
of what's in the box.
And now I'm taking that with
respect to a different variable.
Before it was w naught,
now it's w one.
And the derivative of this
expression here, with respect to
w1,
is now negative xi.
Because negative xi is what's
being multiplied by w1 here.
Is that clear?
Good.
Yeah, good.
There's another question, I
think.
All good?
Okay.
Good.
So now we have our partial
derivatives.
Come on, good notes.
Try it like seven times.
I'm just going to duplicate this
a little bit.
OK,
the copy paste is not behaving
for some reason.
But the thing that I will do to
simplify this a little bit is
that in the first one,
what I will do is I'll take this
minus 1 and this 2,
and I'll bring it outside.
So then I can have a negative 2
over n up front.
Seem OK? So then that first
partial derivative
will be negative 2 over
n times the sum of yi minus w0
plus w1 xi.
For the second partial
derivative,
in which I had a minus xi here,
can I pull the xi out front?
No, you cannot do that, because
it involves i,
and i is the variable that is
being summed over, right? The
way that you should think about
this in a for loop is like,
pretend you said for i in range
1 to n,
do something.
If you use i before the for
loop, it'll say, I don't know
what that is, because that's
only a thing that exists in the
for loop.
Same idea here.
So the negative 2 over n still
sticks around, because there's
still a 2 here,
there's still an over n here,
and there's still a factor of
minus 1,
But there's a factor of xi also
still there,
which is part of the summation.
The thing being summed has an xi
in it.
If it makes it feel less
ambiguous,
is the xi part of it,
nothing's stopping you from just
putting it here,
too.
then it feels a little more
clear that it's part of the
thing being subbed.
Do we agree?
OK.
So now we found the partial
derivative.
What's left?
Allison.
It's from both people.
Excellent.
All we've got to do is set these
equal to 0
and solve for the resulting
combination.
But that's where the algebra
becomes a little tricky.
It's doable.
It's just it would take a lot
more time than we have to
actually do it.
So I'll give you like there's a
couple of things I want to point
out.
And then I'll tell you where it
ends.
First,
let's look at the first
equation.
Why don't I call that one,
call this two.
Look at equation one.
What's the first thing I could
do to simplify it?
Yeah.
Remove the negative 2 over n.
Yeah, remove the negative 2 over
n.
We did that before,
too.
By removing it, I'm multiplying
both sides by negative n over 2.
And what that gives me is the
first condition
that the optimal slope and
intercept have to satisfy.
I can do that with the second
one as well.
Now,
something I want to emphasize is
that this first equation
actually has a convenient
English
interpretation.
It's not obvious when you look
at it because it looks like just
a bunch of random symbols,
but there is a convenient
interpretation.
What do you think that
interpretation is?
What does this say?
It's saying the sum of some
things equals 0.
It's saying there are some
things that if you add them up,
they equal 0.
But what are those things being
summed?
Sum of the errors.
The errors, yeah.
These are just the sum of actual
minus predicted.
Not squared, not absolute valued
or anything because those are
all going to be non-negative, so
they're probably not going to
sum to 0.
But these could be positive or
negative.
This is just saying the sum of
actual minus predicted
if you're using the optimal line
is 0.
What that tells us is whatever
line we end up finding is the
best,
one of the criteria it will
satisfy
is that when you draw it,
the sum of the positive errors
will equal exactly the sum of
the negative errors, Because
those together will have to add
to zero.
And this is like a reoccurring
idea, one that we will see
even a month into the semester
when we revisit all of this
through the lens of linear
algebra.
There we will see why the errors
have to add up to zero from a
linear algebra perspective.
Here we're seeing it as a result
of what the calculus is telling
us.
Just an important thing to know.
English interpretation.
Errors must sum to zero.
This is a sum of actual minus
predicted.
Okay, so now what we need to do
is find the combination
of w0 and
w1.
Now it works.
That together satisfy both of
these conditions.
And again,
I'll tell you the high level
idea.
What we're going to do is in
equation one,
solve for w 0,
but that'll be w 0 star,
it will involve w 1 though.
Right? If I isolate
for w0 here,
it's still going to have a w1 in
it.
So you can think of this as
solving these equations using
substitution.
Like, isolate w0 here,
figure out what that's supposed
to be,
then plug it in here,
but that'll eliminate the w0
here, and that'll tell you what
w1 is supposed to be without any
dependence on w0.
OK?
Then substitute.
into 2 to find w1 star.
That first step we can do
relatively quickly together
here.
Let's look at that first
equation,
the one that said the sum of the
errors had to be 0.
How do I isolate for w0 here?
And now, hopefully, you can see
why in the first lab we had
practice on summation notation
and this kind of thing because
we're dealing with this a lot
here.
How do I isolate for w now?
OK.
Can we start by breaking up the
summation?
Sure.
What does that tell me? Someone
else tell me?
You can do it for me.
Yeah, go for it.
You can do it for someone else.
No, it's OK.
You can do the sum of yi minus
the sum of w0
plus the sum of w1 x1,
or x of i.
Good.
Well, that's also being minused.
But yeah.
OK,
let's talk about how we got
here.
First, note that I implicitly
distributed this minus sign
within the parentheses before
separating the sum.
So inside here,
I have yi minus w0 minus w1 xi.
Then,
using a property that we've used
about summation notation over
the past few lectures,
I broke this up into three
separate sums,
the sum of yi's minus the sum of
w0's minus the sum of w1 xi's.
What questions do we have about
how we arrived here?
Feels OK?
All right,
now let's start simplifying
things where we can.
The sum of the y's,
is there really anything we can
do about that currently?
No,
we'll leave it as is.
The sum of w-noughts,
what can I rewrite that as?
Simplified.
Good.
And remind me of your name
again?
Boyan.
Exactly.
N-w-naught.
Why is that?
Well, this is just adding
w-naught n times.
It's not changing every time
it's being added because there's
no subscript i here.
So this is just going to be
n-w-naught.
And then what can I do about
this last term? the sum of w1
xi's.
Can I do anything there,
Bella?
You can pull out the w1.
Excellent.
Yeah, I can pull out the factor
of w1
because it is a constant.
But the sum of xi is not much I
can do there.
OK,
now we're close to having
isolated for w0.
All I have to do is add n w0 to
both sides.
That'll give me the sum of my
y's minus w1
times the sum of my x's is equal
to n times w0.
What's left? Just divide both
sides by n.
And if I do that here,
well I can erase the n there,
and then divide this by n,
and divide this by n.
And now if I rewrite this
formula for w naught,
what's a simpler way I could
express it?
Andrew.
w naught is equal to the average
of y minus w1 times the average
of x is… Excellent.
Because the sum of y's over n,
that's just the average y, and
the sum of x's over n, that's
just the average x.
Okay?
And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to put stars on these
things,
because these are describing
conditions for the optimal ones.
So now I've found the formula
for the optimal intercept.
But what it's telling me is that
it depends on what the optimal
slope is.
And if you remember yesterday's
lab where you had to program
some of these things,
this is the formula for the
optimal intercept we put there.
And this is the formula for the
optimal intercept you will
always see.
It depends on knowing the
optimal slope first.
So the question is then,
I'll write that best, intercept
depends
on best slope.
The question then is now how do
we find the best slope
in a way that just involves the
x's and y's.
The formula for the best slope
it shouldn't have any other
dependence on it.
Because if that depended on the
best intercept, well, then it's
sort of circular, and I have no
way of figuring out which comes
first.
So I need a formula for the best
slope such that if you told me
all of my raw data points,
x1, y1, x2, y2, and so on, I
could just plug that in, and it
would tell me the best slope.
How am I going to find that?
Remind me.
How am I going to find a formula
for the best slope?
Yeah?
Exactly.
All I'm going to do is I'm going
to take
w knot star equals the average y
minus the best slope times the
average x into what we called
equation two,
which was the sum of xi times yi
minus w0 plus w1 xi.
And when you do that,
ignoring the fact that these
have stars in them,
then this formula down here will
only have three variables or one
actual unknown in it,
w1.
The w0 will disappear because
we've described what w0 is as a
function of w1.
And when you do that,
the only unknown is w1 star.
What you will end up with is a
formula for w1 star.
And again, the algebra really
just follows the same kinds of
steps we just looked at.
Here is the formula you will get
if you follow the steps I've
written out in the notes.
This is the first of many
formulas we will see for the
optimal slope.
It's not the only formula you
will see because you already
know from yesterday's lab that
the formula we gave you there
for the optimal slope looked a
little different.
I'll talk about that in just a
second.
But the main idea is going back
here.
The point of all of this was to
describe
the
line with the lowest mean
squared
error,
OK?
And so that is the line I've
drawn here in orange.
I'll say this line minimizes
mean squared error
on the commute times data set
because its
slope
was
calculated with the formula from
the last
slide
and
again slope is w1 star and its
intercept
w naught star
is the average y minus its
slope times the average x.
And what we've discovered is
that if you,
for any data set,
use that slope formula and that
intercept formula,
the resulting simple linear
regression line
has the lowest mean squared
error of all lines you could
think of.
Does that mean it is always the
best line? Well, it's the best
if what you care about is
minimizing mean squared error.
Again, if you had a different
objective, like minimizing
mean absolute error well then it
wouldn't be the necessarily be
the best right then maybe the
line would have different
properties okay and so this line
in here it's a lot of the
behavior of squared loss that we
talked about last time which is
that for example it's dragged in
the direction of outliers more
than a line that minimizes mean
absolute error would be this is
a question in yesterday's lab if
you remember now there's lots of
names this line,
oops,
lots of names this line goes by
and if you've ever learned about
a line of best fit say like in a
high school stats class or
something like that this was the
one line you looked at,
okay,
even though the formula may have
been described slightly
differently but it gets called
lots Lots of things.
Line of best fit,
the regression line,
least squares,
regression line.
These all are referring to the
line that we've just discovered
through these formulas.
Sound okay?
Questions so far?
Okay.
We're gonna review a little bit
of this when we come back on
Tuesday.
There's just a couple key facts
I want you to be aware of going
into the weekend because they'll
appear on homework 2 which is
going to come out tomorrow.
The first is that there are
several equal or I should
say equivalent and
for
w1 star.
The formula we just saw is one
of them.
Notice the numerator involves x
and y.
Denominator just involves x.
There are a few other equal ways
of writing this.
One way of doing that is with
keeping the same numerator,
but the denominator becomes the
sum of xi minus x bar squared.
So notice here on the bottom,
I had xi times xi minus x bar,
and now I have xi minus x bar
squared.
That's also equal to keeping the
same denominator,
but the numerator becomes xi
minus x bar, which
never appeared on the numerator
before, There was never an x bar
there times yi minus y bar
And you can also let me think of
another color here purple
This is also equal to you keep
the same numerator
And on the sorry the same
denominator and on the numerator
you could do yi times xi minus x
bar
All of these are the same
But it's not obvious why they
should be.
Alex?
Is it useful to memorize these
or do you open them up to the
base form?
Good question.
Let me hold that thought for a
second.
It's fine.
Denominator,
don't you get the square?
Yeah, I'm going to talk about
that in just a second.
So, both of the recent questions
illustrate a bigger point, which
is that you don't need to
memorize all of this.
And in general,
I think when you're studying
math and these sorts of things,
what you should build up is a
strategy or knowledge of how you
would come up with a result
using basic understanding of the
situation, rather than
memorizing all of the facts at
the end.
What I mean by that is the most
versatile of these formulas, for
reasons I'm about to show you is
the one I've just boxed.
It's like the most expanded
version.
And from this,
you can show it's equal to any
of these other ones.
But now your question is, why
are these all equal?
Well,
they actually all use the fact
that the sum of xi minus x bar
is something actually, I don't
know.
You tell me,
what is the sum of xi minus x
bar for an entire data set? It
is always equal to the same
constant,
no matter what the data set is.
What does that equal to, no
matter the data set,
the sum of xi minus x bar?
Always equal to the same number.
Yeah.
0.
Why?
The sum of xi minus x bar is
always equal to 0, no matter the
data set.
It means the balancing point of
the data set and every other
point.
And there's going to be
negatives and positives.
Yeah,
the mean is the point of the
data set where the positive and
negative errors cancel out.
Now, something I didn't
emphasize, but if we switch over
to Lecture 2,
back when we derived that the
mean minimized mean squared
error,
it was hiding in plain sight
from us.
Remember,
the mean squared error there
looked like this.
1 over n times the sum of yi
minus w squared.
And how did we find the optimal
w? Well, we took the derivative
of it, which was this thing, and
set that equal to 0.
But when we set that derivative
equal to 0, we were literally
solving for a w you where the
error is added up to zero.
I just never pointed that out.
But what that tells you is that
the mean is the one point where
the errors add up to zero.
And if you forgot that,
that's fine, because you can
derive it from here.
Because all this is saying is
add up the xi's,
and from that subtract the sum
of the means.
But if you subtract the mean n
times,
That's just n times the mean,
but if you think about what the
formula for the mean is, it's
just the sum of the xi's over n.
So this first thing is also n
times the mean.
So this is zero.
Okay, what does that have to do
with this situation?
Well,
if you look back at this boxed
formula,
you may say like, where did you
get the minus x bar here from?
When the original formula didn't
have the minus X bar, like why
is this numerator equal to this
numerator?
Let me highlight that and this
is the last point I'll make
Why is that the same as this?
Well, now maybe you can start to
see why I illustrated this point
about the sum of the errors
adding up to zero it's because
You can distribute
This term and write this as the
sum of X I Y I minus Y bar
minus another sum
of x bar times yi minus y bar.
But in this second sum, x bar is
a constant.
So in this first sum, I have the
sum of xi yi minus y bar.
In the second sum, I have x bar
times the sum of yi minus y bar.
But what is that?
Remind me?
The sum of yi minus y bar 0.
So I'm left with just the sum of
xi yi minus y bar.
So that is the property I use to
find all of these equivalent
numerators and denominators.
But they can all be derived from
this one boxed version.
You could use that logic to get
there or to get down here.
I removed the minus x bar, but I
could have removed the minus y
bar, it's the same thing.
Now the question is, which one
do you use?
The answer is that it depends on
the situation.
It depends on what the question
is asking and in homework 2 we
have several questions in which
sometimes this is the more
convenient formula Sometimes
this is the more convenient
formula now the last thing I'll
say because you know you gotta
get out of here It's 1151 is
that there's if you look at
chapter 2.4
There's another
formula
For the optimal slope and
intercept that involves what's
called the correlation
coefficient
R,
which you maybe have heard of in
a high school stats class.
Totally fine if you haven't.
The correlation coefficient
times the standard deviation of
y over the standard deviation of
x is also equal to all of those
formulas we just saw.
So when we come back on Tuesday,
we will look at what this means
and what the correlation
coefficient means.
But just know this in case it
comes up in homework two.
And again, I have office hours
after this if you'd like to
chat.
I have two quick questions.
Yeah, yeah.
Can I confuse with the
terminology when you were saying
the summation of the means Sure.
Is it not just the one mean?
Like the mean of the data set,
or my misunderstanding?
So you're talking about y.
You're talking about this.
Ooh, how's that going?
Is it ready?
Remember,
yeah.
But that's just saying x bar
plus x bar plus x bar, which is
n times x bar.
OK,
but it's still the color part of
the thing.
The same one number.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So here,
when we got the homework slide,
Yeah.
I'm confused on why the W sub 1
became the W sub 1 star.
How does finding the optimal?
The star is sort of just like a
thing we tack on at the end to
denote that this is the optimal
one.
Yeah.
I'm confused on why finding the
optimal slope inherently means
that it's not the optimal.
It's more describing that this
is going to be the relationship
between the optimal W0 and W1.
At this stage,
we haven't yet found the optimal
W1.
So if it makes more conceptual
sense, just remove both of the
stars, and then only add them at
the end.
Well, I understand this one,
because you said equal to 0.
But I don't understand how this
one is also the optimal one.
It's less that this,
like,
I see what you're saying.
What this is describing is what
the relationship between the
optimal slope and intercept will
be.
But it's not telling you what
the optimal slope is, just yet.
OK.
The later,
the formula below, or like when
you do the algebra below, that
tells you what the optimal slope
is meant to be.
OK.
Wait, is this what slope is?
Sorry.
Slope, intercept.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, no worries.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Sorry.
Thank you very
much.
You can actually see the screen.
So they finished it like a hour
and a half ago.
So every student gets one.
Oh, geez.
It's speed right now.
I like the way we have a good
time,
which is amazing.
Vanessa, are you still reading?
Oh, we're not reading.
3-0-5.
Do the quiz or whatever those do
at noon.
Does that do at noon? I think it
does at noon.
Which I was just like, well, we
talked about it much earlier.
Did you submit it with your
first name?
I guess it was three stars.
It was two stars first name.
Were you able to submit it
before next Thursday?
Or is it due today? I think it's
due today.
I think that the text films were
always due.
Were there passwords?
Yeah, I did.
I don't know.
I think if you don't know for
us, it was like if you didn't go
to lecture, then it was due next
Thursday.
I couldn't go.
I was like, where are you going
to play? I'm from Michigan.
I'm from Michigan.